<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="1"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-tppy-bmp-seamless-session-01"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="BMP Seamless Session">BMP (BGP Monitoring Protocol)
    Seamless Session</title>

    <author fullname="Thomas Graf" initials="T. " surname="Graf">
      <organization>Swisscom</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Binzring 17</street>

          <city>Zurich</city>

          <code>8045</code>

          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </postal>

        <email>thomas.graf@swisscom.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Paolo Lucente" initials="P." surname="Lucente">
      <organization>NTT</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Siriusdreef 70-72</street>

          <city>Hoofddorp</city>

          <region>WT</region>

          <code>2132</code>

          <country>Netherlands</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>paolo@ntt.net</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Pierre Francois" initials="P." surname="Francois">
      <organization>INSA-Lyon</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city>Lyon</city>

          <code/>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>Pierre.Francois@insa-lyon.fr</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Yunan Gu" initials="Y. " surname="Gu">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Huawei Bld., No.156 Beiqing Rd.</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <code>100095</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>guyunan@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="20" month="February" year="2021"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes a BMP session lifecycle extension to prevent
      data duplication of re-exporting previously exported metrics when BMP
      session is re-established. It prevents loss of metrics between BMP
      session re-establishments to increase overall BMP scalability and
      reduces the possible loss of metrics to a minimum.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="Introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>With the constant increase of BGP paths, the increase of BMP BGP RIB
      coverage from <xref target="RFC8671">RFC8671</xref> and <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-local-rib">draft-ietf-grow-bmp-local-rib</xref>,
      the addition of new TLV's such as <xref
      target="I-D.cppy-grow-bmp-path-marking-tlv">draft-cppy-grow-bmp-path-marking-tlv</xref>
      and <xref
      target="I-D.xu-grow-bmp-route-policy-attr-trace">draft-xu-grow-bmp-route-policy-attr-trace</xref>,
      more BGP metrics and metric dimensions are exported from BMP client to
      server.</t>

      <t>With each BMP session re-establishment, BMP exports the initial BGP
      RIB with BMP route-monitoring messages as described in section 5 of
      <xref target="RFC7854">RFC7854</xref>. Regardless if the same metrics
      where already exported in a previous BMP session or not. This leads to
      data duplication and unnecessary strain of the BMP client and
      server.</t>

      <t>Most times in a network operators network, the BMP session is
      re-established within a short period of time due to connectivity
      interruption or restart of the BMP server due to maintenance. Even
      though, most BMP client implementations support a BMP buffer mechanism,
      metrics are not buffered across BMP session re-establishment, thus
      leading to a loss of metrics.</t>

      <t>Therefore, the proposed BMP session lifecycle improvement covers</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Brief loss of connectivity between BMP client and server</t>

          <t>Seamless Maintenance of BMP server</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>It is based on <xref target="RFC7413">RFC7413, TCP Fast Open</xref>,
      which allows previously established TCP transport sessions to be
      re-established more efficiently.</t>

      <t>This draft describes how the BMP application MUST behave during TCP
      transport re-establishment period in order to prevent metric loss.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Terminology" title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
      [RFC2119] [RFC8174] when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as
      shown here.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Definitions" title="Definitions">
      <t><list hangIndent="5" style="hanging">
          <t
          hangText="Brief loss of connectivity between BMP client and server:">Describes
          a period of time in seconds starting from where the BMP client
          detects loss of connectivity to the BMP server and tries to
          re-establish the TCP session.</t>

          <t hangText="Maintenance of BMP server:">Describes a period of time
          in seconds starting from where the BMP server daemon is restarted
          for maintenance purposes and BMP client tries to re-establish the
          TCP session.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Capability" title="BMP Client and Server Capability">
      <t>To support brief loss of connectivity between BMP client and server,
      the BMP client and server MUST support TCP Fast Open as described in
      <xref target="RFC7413">RFC7413</xref>.</t>

      <t>To support seamless maintenance of BMP server, the BMP client and
      server MUST support TCP Fast Open as described in <xref
      target="RFC7413">RFC7413</xref> and the restart of the BMP server MUST
      distinguish between normal and seamless restart, wherever TCP Fast Open
      cookies are preserved or not.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Lifecycle" title="Updated BMP Session Lifecycle">
      <t>Section 3 of <xref target="RFC7413">RFC7413</xref> describes the TCP
      Fast Open extension in the initial TCP SYN packet and the cookie
      handling during initial and subsequent re-establishment of the TCP
      transport session.</t>

      <t>Section 3.3 of <xref target="RFC7854">RFC7854</xref> describes that
      the BMP session closes with the TCP session. This behavior is extended
      with a configurable BMP session timeout.</t>

      <t>The BMP session timeout starts counting down under the following
      conditions:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Configured value is bigger than 0</t>

          <t>Current TCP session was established with Fast Open extension and
          cookie has been saved</t>

          <t>BMP buffer is not full</t>

          <t>TCP session is going to be terminated</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>The default BMP session timeout is 60 seconds.</t>

      <t>While the time is counting down, all the BMP messages, regardless of
      message type, MUST be buffered. At this stage, the BMP session is still
      considered to be alive.</t>

      <t>When TCP session is re-established with TCP Fast Open extension and
      cookie is identically to previous TCP session, the BMP session remain
      alive, BMP buffer is being exported and normal operation continues.</t>

      <t>When TCP session is re-established without TCP Fast Open extension or
      with TCP Fast Open extension but cookie is not identically to previous
      TCP session, the BMP session is considered terminated and starts with a
      new BMP initiation message.</t>

      <t>When TCP session is not re-established within configured BMP timeout,
      than BMP buffer is discarded and BMP session is considered
      terminated.</t>

      <t>When BMP buffer is full before TCP session is re-established, than
      BMP buffer is discarded and BMP session is considered terminated.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The same security considerations apply as for TCP Fast Open <xref
      target="RFC7413">RFC7413</xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>I would like to thank Pierre Francois, Paolo Lucente and Yunan Gu for
      their review and valuable comments.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7413'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7854'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8671'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-local-rib'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.cppy-grow-bmp-path-marking-tlv'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.xu-grow-bmp-route-policy-attr-trace'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
